Omaha Powwow Project collection
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
Omaha Powwow Project collection 1982-1986
AFC 1986/038
American Folklife Center
2790 items
9 containers
32 sound tape reels: analog; 10 in.
30 sound tape reels: analog; 7 in.
24 sound cassettes (C60 and C90): analog
1,146 photographs: film, negatives, black and white; 35 mm
1,204 photographs: color transparencies; 35 mm (slide format)
32 photographs: prints, black and white; various sizes
10 photographs: prints, color; various sizes
33 photographs: contact sheets, black and white; 8 x 10 in.
4 posters and flyers: color; various sizes
approximately 276 sheets
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Collection contains documentation from Omaha Tribal Powwows 1983-1986, including sound recordings and photographs created by American Folklife Center staff. Additional documentation from the 1983 powwow includes 35 pages of fieldnotes, 30 pages of handwritten tape recording logs, an 8-page program, and three posters. The collection also includes interviews with Omaha tribal members John Turner and Dennis Hastings.
Provenance
Accessioned, 1986.
Accruals
No accruals are expected.
Related Material
These related collections are at the American Folklife Center, Library of Congress:
Alice C. Fletcher and Francis La Flesche collection of Omaha cylinder recordings (AFC 1948/123)
Rufus White and Maxine White interviewed by Gwen Meister, 1993 August 19 (AFC 1993/004)
Omaha Indian interviews collection, 1999 (AFC 1999/014)
Access and Restrictions
The Omaha Powwow Project collection is open to research. To request materials, please contact the Folklife Reading Room at https://hdl.loc.gov/loc.afc/folklife.contact
Certain restrictions to use or copying of materials may apply.
Online Content
The majority of the Omaha Powwow Project collection has been digitized. Selections are available on the Library of Congress website at https://www.loc.gov/collections/omaha-indian-music/about-this-collection/. Other collection materials have been digitized and available; please contact the Folklife Reading Room for more details.
Scope and Content
Collection contains documentation from Omaha Tribal Powwows 1983-1986, including sound recordings and photographs created by American Folklife Center staff. Additional documentation from the 1983 powwow includes 35 pages of fieldnotes, 30 pages of handwritten tape recording logs, an 8-page program, and three posters. The collection also includes interviews with Omaha tribal members John Turner and Dennis Hastings.
Arrangement
The Omaha Powwow Project collection is organized in seven series:
Series 1. Administrative papers and publicity
Series 2. 1983 Omaha Tribal Powwow
Series 3. 1984 Omaha Tribal Powwow
Series 4. 1985 Omaha Tribal Powwow
Series 5. 1986 Omaha Tribal Powwow
Series 6. Interviews conducted by Alan Jabbour
Series 7. Unidentified sound recordings
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Blackbird, Elmer.; Fleischhauer, Carl; Hastings, Dennis; Jabbour, Alan; Kerrey, Robert, 1943-; Lee, Dorothy Sara; Turner, John, 1902-1983
Organizations
American Folklife Center
Subjects
Dance music--Nebraska--Omaha Indian Reservation.; Folk music--Nebraska.; Omaha dance.; Omaha Indians--Interviews.; Omaha Indians--Music.; Omaha Indians--Rites and ceremonies.; Omaha Indians--Social life and customs.; Omaha Indians--Songs and music.; Powwow songs--Nebraska--Omaha Indian Reservation.; Powwows--Nebraska--Omaha Indian Reservation.
Places
Macy (Neb.) event place.; Omaha Indian Reservation (Neb.)--Social life and customs--20th century.
Form/Genre
Correspondence.; Interviews.; Oral histories.; Photographs.; Sound recordings.
Container List
- Series 1: Administrative papers and publicity
  - Correspondence, 1982-1985, 1991-1992 (Box-folder 1/1)
    Includes correspondence with Alan Jabbour, Carl Fleischhauer, Dorothy Sara Lee, Erika Brady, Dennis Hastings, Roger Welsch, John Carter, Mark Merrick, Sr., Joseph E. Harlan, Sr., Marvin F. Kivett, Bob Kerry, Elmer Blackbird, and others.
  - U Mon Hon Hethu'shka Society, undated (Box-folder 1/2)
  - Powwow publicity, 1983-1984 (Box-folder 2/1)
    Posters from the 1983 Powwow were relocated from Box-Folder 1/3.
  - Pow-wow programs and publicity, 1983 (Box-folder 1/3)
    Posters were relocated to Box-Folder 2/1
  - Miscellaneous notes, undated, 9 pages (Box-folder 1/4)
- Series 2: 1983 Omaha Tribal Powwow
  - Subseries 1: Carl Fleischhauer
    Archivist's note: Fleischhauer's original documentation has been used to describe the photos, with minor edits for clarity.
    - Field notes, 1983, 18 pages (Box-folder 1/10)
    - Sub-subseries 1: Black-and-white photographs
      - Black-and-white photo logs, 1983, 30 pages (Box-folder 1/8)
      - Camera roll, August 12, 1983, AFC 1986/038: 214061-1; 38 photographs: film, negatives, black and white; 35 mm (Box 2)
        Archivist's note: the 38 images include frame 00.
        1-6 Flag-lowering ceremony
        7-9 Supper break; spraying down dust
        10-17 Dorothy Lee and Dennis Hastings listen to the tape of Mr. Edward's "Indian Chipmunks"
        18-19 campground and pow-wow from the west
        21-22 "midway"
        23 booth with video games
        24-28 campground/pow-wow from road on the east
        29 looking up road from pow-wow to north
        30-34 spray dust in arena
        35-37 folks eating supper along the south side of the little arena
      - Camera roll, August 12, 1983, AFC 1986/038: 214061-11; 37 photographs: film, negatives, black and white; 35 mm (Box 2)
        2-5 campground
        6-9 the "CBS" TV crew (freelancers from Minneapolis; VTR: Gary Tassone; Cam: Ed Matney (18 N. 4th St., Minneapolis, Minnesota 55401)
        11-16 Robinson family gets ready for evening dance; Norman Robinson with son Seth Robinson (costume) and Norman Jr (sweatshirt) and sister Linda Robinson with Jamie (I am not clear, now, on whether Jamie is Norman's son, or Linda's)
        17-19 in campground
        19 David Blackbird, the "whipman"
        20-21 teenagers
        22 Arena Director, vest
        23-24 Renee Brown and Rosa McCauley
        25-26 gourd dance
        27-32 signing up contest entrants
        33-37 Friday night Grand Entry
      - Camera roll, August 12-13, 1983, AFC 1986/038: 214061-10; 37 photographs: film, negatives, black and white; 35 mm; Night (Box 2)
        1-5 Arena at night from hill (looking east)
        6-7 The "second" drums; Honey Creek Singers in foreground; Tia Piah in background, playing
        8 Charlie Edwards (host drum)
        9-10 looking across host drum; Head Singer Rufus White at extreme left
        18 clown, BIA breechclout; moving counterclockwise
        19-20 Dorothy Lee and M.C. Clifford Wolfe Sr.
        21-22 Grand Entry; senior citizens and Maria LaVigna in foreground, equipment covered with plastic tablecloth- rain
        24-28 Elmer Blackbird, tribal chairman, remarks
        29-34 from east end of arena; looking across crowd (including baby in cradleboard) and dancers toward speaker's stand
      - Camera roll, August 13, 1983, AFC 1986/038: 214061-5; 38 photographs: film, negatives, black and white; 35 mm (Box 2)
        1-5 Bill Kerrey (governor's brother), remarks
        6-8 Eagle dance by group from San Juan Pueblo
        9-12, 15 Princess/stand, watching Eagle dance, note bags for giveaway
        13-14 crowd, including dancers, watch
        17-21 Maria, remarks, presenting the cylinders to tribe
        22-26 Same time, note Wolfe with LaVigna; Wolfe invites whipman and traditional dancers to dance to cylinders
        27-33 dancers dancing to cylinders (the prominent TV crew is NOT CBS; I think it's from Indian Ed. TV)
        34-37 Dorothy Lee hands over tapes to tribal chairman Elmer Blackbird
      - Camera roll, August 13, 1983, AFC 1986/038: 214061-9; 37 photographs: film, negatives, black and white; 35 mm (Box 2)
        1-6 the dance (a special?) for the pow-wow princess the prominent TV crew is the CBS unit
        6-9 at the end of the dance; collecting the money at the speaker's stand, preparing for giveaway
        10-20 Princess giveaway; M.C. Clifford Wolfe Sr. made the remarks for the Princess's mother (grandmother?)
        21-23 fancy dancers get ready in camp area
        24-25 another giveaway; probably the only other one between the Princess's and supper; the attempt here was to get a photo of $ changing hands during the dance
        28-29 two Nagras; D.L. and M.L. in background, mike on stand available for dancers audio, but used only once to try for San Juan singers box with blanket was recordist's chair
        30-31 the two Nagras...
        32-33 mike on stand (rarely used; taken down end Saturday)
        33-34 Speaker's mike; our E-V D056 on left, taped to speaker's own mike
        35-36 stereo pair as suspended above host drum
      - Camera roll, August 13, 1983, AFC 1986/038: 214061-7; 37 photographs: film, negatives, black and white; 35 mm (Box 2)
        1-3 stereo mike pair (Beyer M201N) for host drum
        4 "extra" mike at center of arena, for second drum or women who sang
        5-6 cables and mike stand used as telephone pole to run three cable sets to center of arena
        7-8 singer's area; to show mike cable run and extra mike
        9-13 speaker's stand; man is Charlie Edwards
        15-17 campground to west of arena; boys play football
        18-20 in the campground
        21-22 on midway, place selling "crafts"
        23 midway
        24-27 stand that takes a Polaroid photo; makes button
        29-37 food stand, with fried bread dogs and burgers
      - Camera roll, August 12-13, 1983, AFC 1986/038: 214061-8; 23 photographs: film, negatives, black and white; 35 mm; Photos from August 12 are described as "ruined." Frame 00 is included in the item count. (Box 2)
        This roll is double exposed; the daylight stuff seems to have been made on the twelfth, and the night on the thirteenth. The day stuff (which is available from Kodachrome) includes Maria with her San Juan friend and the Robinson family getting ready by a car. The ruined night stuff includes Paul Brill giving out family tree charts, and Carl Fleischhauer carrying the Nagra to tape the San Juan folks. The only usable images are: 20-21, host drum at night, Tia Piah singers behind.
      - Camera roll, August 13-14, 1983, AFC 1986/038: 214061-13; 35 photographs: film, negatives, black and white; 35 mm (Box 2)
        1-4 host drum
        5-7 Honey Creek Singers
        8-10 host drum
        11-13 member of host drum
        14-15 blank
        16-22 shucking corn; Delia Hallowell, Rosa Linda Wolfe, Ida Anderson
        23-28 Maria LaVigna at her camper
        29-37 Portrait of host drum; two men (or more) missing (see alternates on roll 214061-6, frames 35-37; with all singers)
      - Camera roll, August 13, 1983, AFC 1986/038: 214061-4; 37 photographs: film, negatives, black and white; 35 mm (Box 2)
        1-6 one of the host drum's drums
        7-12 Grand Entry, note that flag is not carried by whipman this time; the whole pow-wow committee joined
        9-12 women dancers, including fancy
        13-18 gate to pow-wow
        19 area to south of small arena; people camped there appear to be black (married to Omaha?)
        20-22 media position; Carl Fleischhauer with AFC equipment in center, John Millar and University of Nebraska at Omaha TV at right (pix by Maria LaVigna)
        23-34 Dance honoring John Turner; "special" and giveaway led by Elmer Blackbird
        36-37 close up of costume of whipman (David Blackbird)
      - Camera roll, August 14, 1983, AFC 1986/038: 214061-3; 38 photographs: film, negatives, black and white; 35 mm (Box 2)
        1-6 Host drum, dancers in background
        7-14 Tia Piah Singers
        15-19 Rufus White, Head Singer, host drum
        20-37 playing with blur, fancy dancers
      - Camera roll, August 14, 1983, AFC 1986/038: 214061-6; 37 photographs: film, negatives, black and white; 35 mm (Box 2)
        2-9 competitors during traditional men's dance contest; I believe #2 is a man named Thomas
        10 singer, throat lozenge, sore throat
        11-13 one of the singers missing in the group photo on roll 214061-13
        14-16 McCauley, other singer missing in the previous group photo
        17-18 money changing hands, in a "special"
        19-20 chair of member of Tia Piah Singers
        21 looking toward Macy from pow-wow (looking east)
        22-24 at main gate, fancy dancer in 22 is Todd Ike
        25-31 taking down the flag at the end of the afternoon
        32-33 dancers leave arena, supper break
        35-37 more complete group picture of singers; names to be obtained from Dennis Hastings (see roll 214061-13, frames 29-37, for alternate versions)
      - Camera roll, August 14, 1983, AFC 1986/038: 214061-12; 37 photographs: film, negatives, black and white; 35 mm (Box 2)
        1-2 Apartment block in Macy
        3-5 (?) Community college
        6-8 Macy main street
        9-21 baseball game
        22-26 crowd at main gate just before evening Grand Entry
        27-28 bumper sticker in midway (on crafts van)
        30-33 a "couples" dance
        34-35 judging fancy dancers
        36-37 judging traditional dancers
      - Camera roll, August 14, 1983, AFC 1986/038: 214061-2; 5 photographs: film, negatives, black and white; 35 mm (Box 2)
        1-2 judging clowns; an arena director calls for applause, no judges per se
        3 one clown
        4-5 water from water bucket
      - Camera roll, August 15, 1983, AFC 1986/038: 214061-14; 19 photographs: film, negatives, black and white; 35 mm (Box 2)
        7-10 Missouri River valley and bluffs from sacred spot
        11-13 tree that looked like a buffalo or cow skull at the same place
        14-16 the clearing at that place (tree in background)
        17-20 river, bluffs, and Iowa land from another place
        21-25 farm on Nebraska state route 94, Thurston County
      - Black-and-white contact sheets, August 12-15, 1983, 14 photographs: contact sheets, black and white; approx. 8 1/2 in. x 11 in. (Box-folder 1/5)
      - Black-and-white photo prints, 1983, 19 photographs: prints, black and white; various sizes (Box-folder 1/6)
    - Sub-subseries 2: Color photographs
      When two boxes are listed, the first box has the preferred version of images, and the second box has similar versions of those images.
      - Color photo logs, 1983, 17 pages (Box-folder 1/9)
      - Camera roll, August 12, 1983, AFC 1986/038: FCP/O-CF-1; 25 photographs: color transparencies; 35 mm (slide format) (Boxes 3, 6)
        1 Whipman David Blackbird brings in flag during Friday afternoon Grand Entry
        2-3 Supper break; spraying down dust
        4-7 Dorothy Lee and Dennis Hastings listen to the tape of Mr Edward's "Indian Chipmunks"
        8-11 campground and pow-wow from the west; 12-13, "midway"
        14-15 booth with videogames
        16-18 campground/pow-wow from road on the east
        19-20 looking up road from pow-wow to north
      - Camera roll, August 12, 1983, AFC 1986/038: FCP/O-CF-2; 28 photographs: color transparencies; 35 mm (slide format); Pencil notes in frame/description area that are difficult to read, not transcribed. (Boxes 3, 6)
        1-2 folks eating supper along the south side of the little arena
        3 campground
        4-5 the "CBS" TV crew (freelancers from Minneapolis; VTR: Gary Tassone; Cam: Ed Matney (18 N. 4th St, Minneapolis, Minnesota 55401)
        7-8 Robinson family gets ready for evening dance; Norman Robinson with son Seth Robinson (costume) and Norman Jr (sweatshirt) and sister Linda Robinson with Jamie (I am not clear, now, on whether Jamie is Norman's son, or Linda's)
        9-10 9-10, in campground
        11-12 David Blackbird, the "whipman"
        13-15 teenagers
        16-17 Arena Director, vest
        18-20 Renee Brown, Adele Grant, and Rosa McCauley
      - Camera roll, August 12, 1983, AFC 1986/038: FCP/O-CF-3; 51 photographs: color transparencies; 35 mm (slide format) (Boxes 3, 6)
        1-2 gourd dance
        3-7 singing up contest entrants
        8-10 Friday nite Grand Entry starts
        11-14 Arena at nite from west
        15 Honey Creek Singers in foreground, Tia Piah singers in background
        16-19 host drum, looking toward west
      - Camera roll, August 12,-13 1983, AFC 1986/038: FCP/O-CF-3A; 19 photographs: color transparencies; 35 mm (slide format); August 12 (night) and August 13 (Box 3)
        1-4 "Intertribal" dance (LaVigna's term) from northeast
        5-6 Dorothy Lee & M.C. Clifford Wolfe Sr.
        7-8 Grand Entry; senior citizens and Maria LaVigna in foreground, equipment covered with plastic tablecloth - rain
        9 Elmer Blackbird, tribal chairman, remarks
        10-11 arena from east, "intertribal" dance
        12 Princess
        13 Arena Director escorts child from arena
        14-15 from east end of arena; looking across crowd (including baby in cradleboard) and dancers toward speaker's stand
        16-19 center of arena at a moment when the Tia Piah singers are the only "second" drum
      - Camera roll, August 13, 1983, AFC 1986/038: FCP/O-CF-4; 24 photographs: color transparencies; 35 mm (slide format) (Boxes 3, 6)
        1 Bill Kerrey (governor's brother), remarks
        2-4 Eagle dance by group from San Juan Pueblo
        5-6 Princess & speakers' stand watching above; note bags for giveaway
        7-8 crowd, including dancers, watch
        9-10 Maria, remarks, presenting the cylinders to tribe
        11-12 Same time, note Wolfe with LaVigna; Wolfe invites whipman and traditional dancers to dance to cylinders
        13-15 dancers dancing to cylinders (the prominent TV crew is not CBS; I think it's from Indian Ed. TV)
      - Camera roll, August 13, 1983, AFC 1986/038: FCP/O-CF-5; 26 photographs: color transparencies; 35 mm (slide format) (Boxes 3, 6)
        1-2 giveaway after the dance (a special?) for the pow-wow princess at the end of the dance; collecting the money
        3-4 Princess giveaway; M.C. Clifford Wolfe Sr. made the remarks for the Princess's mother (grandmother?)
        5-6 fancy dancers get ready in camp area
        7-8 two Nagras; D.L. and M.L. in background, mike on stand available for dancer's audio, but used only once to try for San Juan singers box with blanket was recordist's chair
        9-10 the 2 Nagras...
        11 Speaker's mike; our E-V D056 on left, taped to speaker's own mike
        12-13 stereo pair as suspended above host drum
        14-15 "extra" mike at center; used for second drum or women singers (also visible in 18)
        16-18 mike cables strung out to center from Nagras
      - Camera roll, August 13, 1983, AFC 1986/038: FCP/O-CF-6; 24 photographs: color transparencies; 35 mm (slide format) (Boxes 3, 6)
        1-4 speaker's stand; man is Charlie Edwards
        5-6 campground to west of arena; boys play football
        7 on midway, place selling "crafts"
        8-9 stand that takes a Polaroid photo; makes button
        10-13 food stand, with fried bread dogs and burgers
        14-16 craft stand (again)
        17-18 waiting for the john
        19-20 preparing for contest: fancy dancer DeWayne Wabasha, with parents Rick and Brenda and sister Terri: 617 W. 8th, Sioux City, Iowa 51103
      - Camera roll, August 13, 1983, AFC 1986/038: FCP/O-CF-7; 27 photographs: color transparencies; 35 mm (slide format); Pencil notes in frame/description area that are difficult to read, not transcribed. (Boxes 3, 6)
        1-4 Honey Creek Singers
        5 Tia Piah singers
        6 host drum
        7-9 individuals at Tia Piah singers
        10 host drum individual
        11-13 a "couples" dance
        14 clown with hula hoops
        15 clowns
        16 judging fancy dancers' regalia
        17-19 Paul Brill gives out family tree charts; man in frame 18 is tribal chm Elmer Blackbird; Men's fancy dance wasn't judged until Saturday night, Paul handed out genealogies both nights, Saturday with little fanfare
      - Camera roll, August 13, 1983, AFC 1986/038: FCP/O-CF-8; 27 photographs: color transparencies; 35 mm (slide format); Pencil notes in frame/description area that are difficult to read, not transcribed. (Boxes 3, 6)
        1-3 Maria LaVigna and an unidentified person from San Juan Pueblo
        4-8 shucking corn; Delia Hallowell, Rosa Linda Wolfe, Ida Anderson - in 6-8, add M.L. & Dorothy Lee
        9-10 Maria LaVigna at her camper
        11-12 Portrait of host drum; two men (or more) missing (see alternates on AFC 1986/038: FCP/O-CF-13, images 4-6, with all singers)
        13-16 host singers and one of their drums
      - Camera roll, August 13-14, 1983, AFC 1986/038: FCP/O-CF-9; 26 photographs: color transparencies; 35 mm (slide format); Addition of date in pencil; used both dates. (Boxes 3, 6)
        1 Grand Entry, note that flag is not carried by whipman this time; the whole pow-wow committee joined the march
        2 pow-wow banner
        3 shawl worn by female member of pow-wow committee
        4-11 grand entry
        4 end of male traditional dancers; start of fancy
        6 fancy still coming in outer ring; flag-carrier on inner ring of spiral
        8 women dancers (shawl dancers?)
        10-11 women fancy dancers
        12-13 gate to pow-wow
        14 area to south of small arena; people camped there appear to be black (married to Omaha?)
        15 San Juan buffalo dance, presumably taken by Maria LaVigna
        16 media position; Carl Fleischhauer with AFC equipment in center, John Millar and University of Nebraska at Omaha TV at right (by Maria LaVigna)
        17-19 Dance honoring John Turner; "special" and giveaway led by Elmer Blackbird
      - Camera roll, August 13, 1983, AFC 1986/038: FCP/O-CF-10; 29 photographs: color transparencies; 35 mm (slide format) (Boxes 3, 6)
        1-4 Giveaway honoring John Turner; "special" and giveaway led by Elmer Blackbird
        5-6 close up of costume of whipman (David Blackbird)
        7-8 Kenny Blackbird, a grandson (?) of John Turner, plays the Omaha flute, flanked by Clifford Wolfe Sr and Elmer Blackbird (relationship unknown)
        9-11 host drum
        12-14 Tai Piah singers
        15 woman dancer (probably "fancy," may be shawl)
        16-17 Head Singer of host drum, Rufus White
      - Camera roll, August 14, 1983, AFC 1986/038: FCP/O-CF-11; 27 photographs: color transparencies; 35 mm (slide format) (Boxes 3, 6)
        1-12 playing with blur, fancy dancers
        13-14 Two arena directors with a fancy dancer with two things on the ground. I believe the two grounded items are held in the dancers hands while dancing. If regalia is dropped or falls off during a dance, a special procedure is called for; this may be such an event. Or, the dancer felt ill. I don't know.
        15-20 Male traditional dancers
      - Camera roll, August 14, 1983, AFC 1986/038: FCP/O-CF-12; 24 photographs: color transparencies; 35 mm (slide format) (Boxes 4, 6)
        1-2 chair of member of Tia Piah Singers
        3-4 looking toward Macy from pow-wow (looking east)
        6-14 at main gate, fancy dancer in 6 and 7 is Todd Ike
        15-16 taking down the flag at the end of the afternoon
        17-20 dancers leave arena, supper break
      - Camera roll, August 14, 1983, AFC 1986/038: FCP/O-CF-13; 26 photographs: color transparencies; 35 mm (slide format) (Boxes 4, 6)
        1-2 Rosa McCauley and Renee Brown
        3 CF taken by one of the girls
        4-6 complete host drum singers; name id's to be obtained from Dennis Hastings; see alternates on AFC 1986/038: FCP/O-CF-8, frames 11-12